Register of the Library of Social History Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Library of Social History collection
1894-2000
91004
Hoover Institution Archives
307 manuscript boxes, 2 card file boxes, 1 oversize boxes (158.2 linear feet)
Serial issues, pamphlets, leaflets, internal bulletins, other internal documents, and electoral and convention material, issued by Trotskyist groups throughout the world, and especially in the United States, Latin America and Western Europe, and including some materials issued by non-Trotskyist left-wing groups; speeches and writings by Fidel Castro and other Cuban leaders, and printed matter relating to Cuba, with indexes thereto; speeches and writings by Nicaraguan Sandinista leaders; and public and internal issuances of the New Jewel Movement of Grenada and its leaders, and printed and other material relating to the movement and its overthrow. Collected by the Library of Social History (New York City), an affiliate of the Socialist Workers Party of the United States. Does not include issuances of the Socialist Workers Party.
Library of Social History (New York, N. Y.)
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The Library of Social History Collection, as its name indicates, was originally brought together by the Library of Social History in New York City. An affiliate of the Socialist Workers Party, the Library of Social History gradually assembled and maintained the collection over a period of decades prior to its acquisition by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1991.
Scope and Content Note
Materials within the Library of Social History Collection fall naturally into four distinct series. By far the largest of these, constituting three-fourths of the entire collection, is the Fourth International Series. This consists of issuances of national sections of the Fourth International from all parts of the world and may well be the most comprehensive body of such material in existence. Issuances include internal bulletins, internal circulated documents, short serial runs (many serial titles existed for only a few issues or even a single issue), pamphlets, leaflets, and other ephemeral publications. Long serial runs have been transferred to the Hoover Institution Library. The series is arranged alphabetically by country of origin, and thereunder alphabetically by issuing organization. A multiplicity of issuing organizations will be noted in the cases of many countries. Simple name changes, reorganizations following upon splits or mergers, existence of organizations in different time periods, amicable coexistence of related organizations (e.g., adult and youth parties), and hostile coexistence of rival organizations, are all factors contributing to this proliferation of names. Materials are listed under the name of the issuing organization at the time of issuance. The complexity of organizational histories has prohibited any attempt at cross-referencing names of organizations. Researchers who require assistance in this regard may find Robert J. Alexander, International Trotskyism, 1929-1985: A Documented Analysis of the Movement (Durham, N.C., 1991), a useful resource. While the great bulk of material in the collection stems from organizations formally affiliated to the Fourth International or otherwise Trotskyist-derived, there is a certain amount of material issued by left-wing organizations outside the Trotskyist heritage, or, rarely, by organizations altogether outside left-wing or socialist movements. Any material that cannot be meaningfully assigned to an issuing organization has been placed at the end of the listings for the country in question. Material on the United States does not include issuances of the Socialist Workers Party, which was for decades the American fraternal party of the Fourth International, or of its predecessors or affiliates. (For this, see the separate Socialist Workers Party Records in the Hoover Institution Archives, and holdings of the Hoover Institution Library.) United States materials are nevertheless voluminous, including issuances of rival organizations, materials on the trade-union, unemployed and women's movements, and a large number of Communist Party pamphlets.
The other three series of the Library of Social History Collection are thematically related. The Cuban Revolutionary Government Series is devoted to speeches and writings of leaders of the revolutionary government that came to power in Cuba in 1959 under the aegis of the Movimiento Revolucionario 26 de Julio. The Nicaraguan Revolutionary Government Series covers speeches and writings of leaders of the Frente Sandinista de Liberació n Nacional revolutionary government of 1979 to 1990 in Nicaragua. The Grenadian Revolutionary Government Series covers speeches and writings of leaders of the New Jewel Movement revolutionary government of 1979 to 1983 in Grenada. As might be expected in light of the durability of its subject, the Cuban Revolutionary Government Series is much the largest of these three. Speeches and writings of Fidel Castro through 1991 alone account for more than 30 manuscript boxes. Arrangement of all three series is parallel. Within each series materials are listed alphabetically by name of individual revolutionary leader and thereunder in chronological order. Materials are printed in most cases, but derived from such diverse sources as to render the aggregate unique and its duplication impracticable. At the end of each series are materials not attributable to a single leader. Wherever possible these are listed alphabetically by issuing agency. The Grenadian Revolutionary Government Series also includes a microfiche set of Grenadian documents captured by U.S. armed forces.
All materials in the collection relating to Cuba, Nicaragua and Grenada are concentrated in the last three series. Consequently there are no entries for these countries in the Fourth International Series. A modest amount of material on Fourth International affiliates in Cuba and Nicaragua may be found in the Cuban and Nicaraguan Revolutionary Government Series respectively.
Scope and Content of the Incremental Materials, Part I
The Hoover Institution Archives acquired holdings of the Library of Social History, New York City, in 1991. A Register to the Library of Social History Collection was prepared in 2000 and remains the principal overall description of and finding aid to the collection. Since its preparation additional shipments of material have been received, boxes 266-307.
The most significant portion of the addendum is the Nicaraguan Revolutionary Government Series, which is a continuation of the series of the same name in the main body of the collection. It consists of issuances of and materials about the Frente Sandinista de Liberació n Nacional (FSLN) revolutionary government of Nicaragua from 1979 to 1990. Most of this material is printed or near-print but is derived from such diverse sources as to make it a uniquely valuable documentary resource. It includes documentation on the origins and early factional struggles within the FSLN prior to the revolution of 1979; writings of and biographical materials about the FSLN founder Carlos Fonseca Amador; statutes, official reports and statistics documenting FSLN governmental programs; international assessments of the government's performance (mainly from academic journals and from left-wing theoretical journals); and documentation of the decline and fall of the FSLN government. It also includes many speeches, statements and interviews of FSLN government leaders, notably Daniel Ortega (president), Sergio Ramírez (vice president), Tomás Borge (minister of the interior), Humberto Ortega (minister of defense), Ernesto Cardenal (minister of culture), Henry Ruíz (minister of planning), Jaime Wheelock (minister of agriculture and agrarian reform), Luís Carrió n (deputy minister of the interior), Bayardo Arce, and Victor Tirado.
Foldering of materials by the Library of Social History has been largely retained. Folders tended to fall into two categories-those whose contents were from the same narrow time frame and those whose contents had a common topical theme. The dual criteria of arrangement suggested division of the series into a Chronological Subseries and an Alphabetical (topical) Subseries. Most materials relating to the earliest period and to the latest period of FSLN history respectively will be found in the Chronological Subseries, while most materials relating to substantive activities of the FSLN while in government power during the intervening period will be found in the Alphabetical Subseries. Researchers will wish to consult both subseries, however.
The General Subject File consists of material on a variety of topics relevant to international twentieth-century revolutionary movements. These include the Fourth International and its sections in various countries; Soviet anti-Trotskyism and political trials; social legislation in the Soviet Union; the Soviet-Yugoslav breach; the revolutionary governments of Cuba and Grenada; and revolutionary struggle in South Africa. The material consists mostly of pamphlets and other printed items, but there is also noteworthy unpublished material. This includes academic dissertations and other typescript studies; a multi-volume collection of writings by Ernesto Guevara, typeset but apparently unpublished; and a multi-volume documentary history of revolutionary movements in South Africa, likewise typeset but unpublished.
A series of Monographs contains substantial printed volumes on similar subjects. Other books and serial runs have been incorporated into the holdings of the Hoover Institution Library.
A small Audiovisual File includes miscellaneous items, notably a number of mounted photographs of Barcelona during the Spanish Civil War. There is also a small Oversize File.
Scope and Content of the Incremental Materials, Part II
The Hoover Institution Archives acquired holdings of the Library of Social History, New York City, in 1991. A register to the collection was prepared in 2000 and remains the principal overall description of and finding aid to the collection. Since its preparation additional shipments of material have been received. The Incremental Materials II series describes a portion of this material. It primarily concerns Cuba and notably includes a collection of writings by Ché Guevara.
Castro, Fidel, 1926-; Fourth International.; Frente Sandinista de Liberació n Nacional.; Library of Social History (New York, N.Y.); New Jewel Movement.; Communism--Europe.; Communism--Latin America.; Communism--United States.; Communism.; Cuba--History--1959-; Cuba--Politics and government--1959-; Cuba.; Europe.; Grenada--Politics and government--1974-1983.; Grenada.; Latin America.; Nicaragua--Politics and government--1979-1990.; Nicaragua.; Socialism--Europe.; Socialism--Latin America.; Socialism--United States.; Socialism.; United States--Politics and government.
- Fourth International Series, 1894-1991 (Box 1-199)
  Scope and Contents note
  Internal bulletins, serial issues, pamphlets, and leaflets, issued by national sections of the Fourth International and other Trotskyist-derived groups in many countries. Includes some issuances of non-Trotskyist left-wing and other organizations. Arranged alphabetically by country and thereunder alphabetically by issuing organization.
  - General. Bibliographies and indexes to contents of internal bulletins of international bodies of the Fourth International and to international internal bulletins of national sections, 1930-1940 (Box-folder 1: 1-7)
  - Albania. Partia e Punës së Shqipërisë (Box 2)
    - Information Bulletin of the Central Committee of the Party of Labor of Albania. Vol. 19 no. 4, (1967) (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Pamphlets
      - Adil Çarçani, Speech Delivered to the Solemn Meeting Commemorating the 46th Anniversary of the Great October Socialist Revolution and the 22nd Anniversary of the Founding of the Party of Labor of Albania; For the Militant Unity of the Communist Movement under the Victorious Banner of Marxism-Leninism; Khrushchev Rehabilitates the Agents of Imperialism and Supports the Murderers of Communists; The Khrushchev-Tito Revisionist Group Concoct New Plans against the Cause of Socialism; Let Us Hold Aloft the Revolutionary Banner of the Moscow Declarations and Protect Them from the Attacks of the Modern Revisionists; The Moscow Declaration, the Invincible Banner of the War against Imperialism and Revisionism; Slanders and Fabrications Cannot Stand Up to Facts and Documents, 1963 (Box-folder 2: 2)
      - The Dissentient Activity of the Khrushchevian Revisionists in the Light of M. Suslov's Report; N. Khrushchev Distorts Lenin's Ideas in Order to Justify His Own Pro-Imperialist Line of Action; An Open Letter to the Members of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union; Togliati's "Testament," the Crisis of Modern Revisionism and the Fight of Marxist-Leninists, 1964 (Box-folder 2: 3)
      - Documents in Connection with the Meeting of the Political Consultative Committee of the Warsaw Treaty Which Was Held from January 19 to 20, 1965; The Khrushchevite Brezhnev-Kosigin-Mikoyan Troika Are on the Way to Negating and Sabotaging the Liberation Wars of Peoples; Khrushchevite Revisionists Take One Further Dangerous Step towards Capitalist Degeneration of Socialist Economy; What Lies Behind the Divisive Meeting of March 1 Which the Khrushchevite Revisionists Are Getting Up (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Communist and Workers' Parties and Marxist-Leninist Groups Greet the Fifth Congress of the Party of Labor of Albania; Everlasting Friendship; A New Plot of the Khrushchevite Revisionists against the Interests of the Socialist Countries; Shameful Failure of the Political and Economic System of Titoite Yugoslavia; Mehmet Shehu, Speech Delivered at the First Session of the VI Legislature of the Popular Assembly of the People's Republic of Albania; The 23d Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union Sanctified the General Line of Khrushchevite Revisionism, Their Policy of Treason and Capitulation; What "Gifts" Are the Italian Revisionists Taking with Them to Their XIth Congress, 1966 (Box-folder 2: 5)
      - On Some Aspects of the Problem of the Albanian Woman, 1967 (Box-folder 2: 6)
      - The Soviet Revisionists and Czechoslovakia; Where Is Czechoslovakia Heading For?, 1968 (Box-folder 2: 7)
      - The Demagogy of the Soviet Revisionists Cannot Conceal Their Traitorous Countenance, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Algeria
    - Comité de Liaison des Trotskystes Algériens
      - L'étincelle. No. 3, (1976) (Box-folder 2: 9)
      - Tribune algérienne. No. 7-8, no. 9, (1976) (1977) (Box-folder 2: 10)
      - Internal circulated documents, 1976 (Box-folder 2: 11)
      - Leaflets, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - Comité pour la Défense d'Ahmed Ben Bella et des Autres Victimes de la Répression en Algérie. Pamphlet. Qu'est devenu Ben Bella?, (1967) (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - Front de Libération Nationale. Pamphlets. The Tripoli Program; Ahmed Ben Bella, Discours; Appel addressé à tous les militants hommes et femmes qui sont à l'intérieur et à l'extérieur du parti F.L.N., (1962) (1963) (1964) (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Angola. Comité Chileno de Solidaridad con la Resistencia Antifascista. Pamphlet. Angola: Proceso al mercenarismo, (1976) (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Antilles
    - Centre d'Information Guadeloupe Guyane Martinique. C.I.G.G.M. No. 17, n.n., (1988) (1990) (Box-folder 2: 16)
    - Combat Ouvrier
      - Combat ouvrier. No. 58, 61-63, 69, no. 72-81, no. 372, (1976) (1977) (1986) (Box-folder 2: 17)
      - Pamphlet. Manifeste, (1972) (Box-folder 2: 18)
    - Federated Workers' Trade Union. Pamphlet. Rules, (1944) (Box-folder 2: 19)
    - Groupe Révolution Socialiste (Box 3)
      - Libération Antilles-Guyane. No. 4-5, no. 6-11, no. 12-15, 17, n.n., no. 20-22, (1972) (1973) (1974) (1975) (Box-folder 3: 1)
      - Lutte communiste. No. 1, no. 2-3, 6, n.n., (1974) (1975) (Box-folder 3: 2)
      - Tranchées. No. 9, n.n., no. 11/12, (1985) (1986) (Box-folder 3: 3)
      - Pamphlets. Courbain contre Messmer: Procès colonial; Vincent Placoly, Portrait d'un dictateur; Philippe Pierre-Charles, La Jamaique à la croisée des chemins, (1972) (1974) (1976) (Box-folder 3: 4)
      - Leaflets, 1974 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Argentina
    - Comisión Provisoria de Reorganización de la Sección Argentina [United Secretariat]. Boletín interno de discusión e informació n. No. 1, (1980) (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Comité de Dirección Paritario. Revolución socialista. No. 1, (1976) (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Comité de Unificación del Movimiento Cuartainternacionalista Argentina
      - Boletín de discusión. N.n., (1941) (Box-folder 3: 8)
      - Pamphlet. Proyecto de resolución organizativa sobre el partido, (1941) (Box-folder 3: 9)
      - Leaflet, clipping, 1941 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - Confederación General del Trabajo. CGT. No. 58 (1970) (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - Ejército Revolucionario del Pueblo
      - Estrella roja. No. 5, no. 10, 14, n.n., (1971) (1972) (1973) (Box-folder 3: 12)
      - Communiqués. Printed in Cuadernos de politica internacional no. 3, (1972) (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - Estudiantes contra la Represión. Represión. No. 1, n.n., (1972) (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - Fracción Bolchevique
      - Nuevo curso. No. 1-2, (1974) (Box-folder 3: 15)
      - Socialismo y revolución. N.n., (n.d.) (Box-folder 3: 16)
      - Internal circulated documents, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 3: 17)
      - Pamphlet. El peronismo ayer hoy, (1972) (Box-folder 3: 18)
    - Fracción Roja. Resolutions, leaflets, banners, 1973 (Box-folder 3: 19)
    - Frente de Sanidad. Boletín interno. N.n., (1972) (Box-folder 3: 20)
    - Grupo Combate [Sweden]
      - Argentina. N.n., (1979) (Box-folder 3: 21)
      - En lucha por el poder obrero y el socialismo. No. 1, no. 2, (1980) (1980-1981) (Box-folder 3: 22)
      - Leaflets, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 3: 23)
    - Grupo Cuarta Internacional
      - Boletín de información internacional. No. 6, (1950) (Box-folder 3: 24)
      - Proletarios del mundo, unios! No. 1, no. 2, n.n., (1945) (1946) (Box-folder 3: 25)
      - Pamphlets. Leon Trotsky, El militanter evolucionario y el partido obrero; Leon Trotsky, Los sindicatos en la epoca del imperialismo, (ca. 1946) (ca.1946) (Box-folder 3: 26)
    - Grupo Espartaco [first]. Espartaco. No. 1, (1946) (Box-folder 3: 27)
    - Grupo Espartaco [second] (Box 4)
      - Bandera roja. No. 4-5, no. 7-9, no. 10-14, (1971) (1972) (1973) (Box-folder 4: 1)
      - Boletín de polemica. No. 1, (1972) (Box-folder 4: 2)
      - Leaflets, 1972 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Grupo Obrero Revolucionario [first]. Pamphlets
      - General. La Argentina frente a la guerra mundial; La agonia mortal del capitalismo y las tareas de la Cuarta internacional, (1940) (1941) (Box-folder 4: 4)
      - Quebracho. Como salir del pantano; Nuestras perspectivas politicas; Por el socialismo revolucionario y por la Cuarta internacional; Qué quiere la Cuarta internacional; La revolución mundial y la traición stalinista; Centrismo, oportunismo y bolchevismo, (1939) (1939) (1939) (1939) (1939) (1940) (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - Grupo Obrero Revolucionario [second]
      - Combate socialista. No. 2, 4, no. 6-8, (1976) (1977) (Box-folder 4: 6)
      - Internal circulated documents, 1976 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Grupo Praxis
      - Boletín interno praxis. No. 21, 24, (1985) (Box-folder 4: 8)
      - Unida izquierda. No. 5-7, 9, no. 10, no. 12, (1986) (1987) (1988) (Box-folder 4: 9)
      - Leaflets, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - Izquierda Nacional
      - Política. No. 2, (1958) (Box-folder 4: 11)
      - Pamphlets
        - Jorge Abelardo Ramos, Crisis y resurección de la literatura argentina; Jorge Abelardo Ramos, Manuel Ugarte y la revolució n latinoamericana; Juan Alvarez, Las guerras civiles argentinas; Eduardo B. Astesano, San Martín y el origen del capitalismo argentino; Juan Bautista Alberdi, Mitre al desnudo; Abraham Guillen, Historia de la revolución española; Jorge E. Spilimbergo, La revolución nacional en Marx, 1961 (Box-folder 4: 12)
        - Ricardo Carpani, Arte y revolución en América latina; Alberto Methol Ferré, La izquierda nacional en la Argentina; Jorge E. Spilimbergo, Juan B. Justo o el socialismo cipayo; Vivian Trias, El imperialismo en el Rio de la Plata, undated (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - Juventud Socialista
      - La chispa. No. 1-2, 5-7, no. 15-16, (1974) (1975) (Box-folder 4: 14)
      - Leaflets, 1974 (Box-folder 4: 15)
    - Liga Comunista (Box 5)
      - Revolución. No. 1-4, no. 6-7, (1974) (1975) (Box-folder 5: 1)
      - Leaflet, n.d. (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - Liga Comunista Revolucionaria. Leaflets, n.d. (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - Liga de Estudio y Acción Revolucionaria Marxista. Internal circulated document, 1975 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - Liga Obrera Revolucionaría
      - Boletín interno. No. 1, no. 2, (1941) (1942) (Box-folder 5: 5)
      - Boletín sudamericano. No. 1-3, 5, (1943) (Box-folder 5: 6)
      - Lucha obrera. Vol. 3 no. 16-18, (1941) (Box-folder 5: 7)
      - Documentos para la unificación del movimiento cuartainternacionalista argentino bulletin series, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 5: 8)
      - Leaflets, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - Liga Obrera Socialista. Boletín de discusión. No. 3, (1941) (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - Liga Socialista Revolucionaría
      - Boletín en el exterior de la LSR. No. 1, (1979) (Box-folder 5: 11)
      - Frente obrero. N.n., (1977) (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - Movimiento al Socialismo
      - M.A.S. No. 0-1, (1982) (Box-folder 5: 13)
      - Pamphlet. Programa del MAS, (1985) (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - Movimiento de la Izquierda Revolucionaría
      - El militante. Vol. 2 no. 14-15, (1963) (Box-folder 5: 15)
      - Internal circulated document, 1963 (Box-folder 5: 16)
    - Movimiento los de Abajo. Los de abajo. Vol. 2 no. 14-16, (1989) (Box-folder 5: 17)
    - Movimiento Política Obrera
      - Adelante! No. 1-12, no. 13-15, (1976) (1977) (Box-folder 5: 18)
      - América India. No. 1, (1972) (Box-folder 5: 19)
      - Correo internacional. No. 1-2, (1975) (Box-folder 5: 20)
      - Tribuna. Vol. 2 no. 16-22, no. 25, (1977) (1978) (Box-folder 5: 21)
      - Pamphlets. La juventud se organiza para luchar por el gobierno obrero y popular y el socialismo; Por una tendencia sindical clasista de masas; Respuesta política a la campaña provocadora de la direcció n del P.S.T.; Respuesta de Política obrera al PST; Por el esclarecimiento del asesinato de los compañeros de Miluz, Jorge Fisher y Miguel Angel Bufano, (1971) (1971) (1973) (1974) (1975) (Box-folder 5: 22)
      - Leaflets, 1965-1979 (Box-folder 5: 23)
      - Educational material (circulated reprints), circa 1976-1977 (Box-folder 5: 24)
    - Organización Montoñeros. Evita montoñera. No. 1, (1973) (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Orientación Socialista. Manifiesto. No. 1-5, n.n., no. 12, (1975) (1976) (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Palabra Obrera
      - Boletín interno. No. 13, 16-17, 19, (1964) (Box-folder 6: 3)
      - Quehacer. No. 0, no. 2-4, (1960) (1961) (Box-folder 6: 4)
      - Pamphlets. Esto es Palabra obrera; Balance cubano; Latinoamérica y Cuba; Ezequiel Reyes, Que es la izquierda; Terrorismo, (1959?) (circa 1960) (1961) (1961) (1964) (Box-folder 6: 5)
      - Leaflets, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - Partido Obrero (Trotskista)
      - Vanguardia obrera. Vol. 2 no. 16, n.n., (1963) (Box-folder 6: 7)